In the previous slides,
前のスライドでは
I drew the mathematical model in a specific form.
特定の形式の数学的モデルを描きました
The model consists of many layers arranged to one after the other.
モデルには多数の層が順番に配置されています
The input passes through the first layer,
入力は最初の層を通り
and then the second,
次に2層目
and then the third, et cetera,
さらに3層目から先を通っていきます
with each of the layers themselves being a simple mathematical function.
それぞれの層が単純な数学関数です
So, the entire model consists of a function,
つまりモデル全体がいくつもの関数の連なりで できているということです
The diagram depicts a mathematical model called a neural network.
この図はニューラルネットワークという 数学モデルを表しています
There are other common mathematical models used in machine learning,
機械学習の一般的な数学モデルは この他にもあります
linear methods, decision trees,
線形法 決定ツリー
radial basis functions, ensembles of trees,
放射基底関数 集団決定ツリー
radial basis functions, followed by linear methods, the list goes on.
放射基底関数からの線形法などです
But we're talking about neural networks.
ここでは ニューラルネットワークを取り上げます
Traditionally, neural network models didn't have this many layers.
従来 ニューラルネットワークモデルに これほど多数の層はありませんでした
Neural networks date back to the 1970s,
ニューラルネットワークは 1970年代に生まれましたが
but they used to have only one hidden layer.
当時は隠れ層が1つのみでした
The reason had to do with number one, computational power,
第1の理由は 計算能力の問題です
training deep neural networks,
深層ニューラルネットワークや
neural networks with lots of layers takes a lot of computing power.
何層ものニューラルネットワークの訓練には 膨大な計算能力が必要です
Second reason, they had only one hidden layer, availability of data.
第2の理由はデータ不足です
As you add more layers,
層が増えるにつれ
there are more and more weights to adjust,
より多くの調整が重要になってきます
so you need lots of more data.
つまり より多くのデータが必要です
And the third reason why you had only one hidden layer, computational tricks.
第3の理由は計算技術です
It turns out that if you just add layers,
単に層を増やすだけでは
you will run into some issues,
問題が生じます
the neural networks will take a long time to train,
ニューラルネットワークの訓練には 長い時間がかかり
some of the layers will become all zero or they'll blow up,
属によっては すべてゼロになったり 破たんして
and become all NAM or not a number.
数値ではないNAMになったりします
So, the research community had to develop a number of tricks and
そのため 研究者はさまざまな技法を開発して
techniques to get deep neural networks to work.
深層ニューラルネットワークの 働きを改善しました
So, in the last few years neural networks have proven themselves to
ここ数年 ニューラルネットワークは
be the best or near best in a wide variety of tasks,
さまざまな問題で最適か ほぼ最適なモデルとなりました
even tasks that used to be thought to be unsolvable with machine learning.
機械学習では解決不可能と 思われていた問題でもです
Neural networks have enable dramatic improvements in
ニューラルネットワークは 言語翻訳、画像分類、音声認識など
really hard problems like language translation,
非常に困難な課題において
image classification, speech understanding, et cetera.
劇的な向上をとげました
And they work just as well or better unstructured data problems,
また 非構造化データにおいても サポートベクターマシンやブースティング決定木
that's traditional machine learning methods such as
バギング決定木のような 従来の機械学習の方法と
support factor machines are boosted or bagged decision trees,
同等以上に機能します
and you can see this at Google.
Googleでも利用しています
The use of deep learning at Google has accelerated rapidly.
Googleでの深層学習の使用は 急速に増加しています
We had pretty much no deep learning models four years ago,
4年前は 深層学習モデルは ほとんどありませんでしたが
and now we have more than 4,000 deep learning models within Google.
今では 4,000を超える深層学習モデルが Googleに存在します
So, in this specialization,
この専門コースでは
we will use neural networks almost exclusively.
ほぼニューラルネットワークのみを使用します
We will start off unstructured data problems,
まず 非構造化データに関する問題から始め
and once we know how to build an end-to-end pipeline,
エンドツーエンドの パイプラインの構築方法を学んだら
we will take that knowledge,
その知識を利用して
and show you how to do image problems,
画像問題
and sequence problems, and recommendation systems.
シーケンス問題 そして推奨システムについてお話します
But look again at this graph, 4,000-plus models.
ここでもう一度 4,000を超えるモデルをご覧ください
How can there be so many ML models?
なぜこれほど多くの 機械学習モデルがあるのでしょうか
Well, ML is part of pretty much every Google product out there,
機械学習がほとんどのGoogleプロダクトに 組み込まれているからです
whether it's YouTube or Play or Chrome or Gmail or Hangouts,
YouTube、Play、Chrome、 Gmail、Hangouts
they all use Machine Learning.
これらすべてに機械学習が使用されています
It's not that there is just one ML model at YouTube.
そして YouTubeであれ何であれ 使われる機械学習モデルは1つではありません
There are dozens of ML models per product.
1つのプロダクトに 何十という機械学習モデルが使われています
In my experience, this is something that takes some getting used to.
個人的には この事実に慣れるまでには 少し時間がかかりました
You might look at a business problem, say,
ビジネスの問題を考えてみましょう
how to forecast rather an item will go out of stock
たとえば 在庫が切れるかどうか 予測するとします
and think of it as a single Machine Learning model that you have to build.
これを1つの機械学習モデルとして考えます
But in practice, to forecast whether an item will go out of stock,
しかし実際には 在庫が切れるかどうかを予測するには
you will have to build many Machine Learning models to solve the problem.
多数の機械学習モデルが必要です
You may have to break this problem down into
ビジネスの知識に基づいてこの問題を
smaller problems based on your knowledge of the business.
複数の小さい問題に分割する必要があります
For example, your first model might be to predict
たとえば1つ目のモデルでは
the demand for the product at the store location,
ある店舗での製品の需要を予測し
and your second model might predict the inventory of
2つ目のモデルでは
You might need a third model to predict how long it's
3つ目のモデルも必要かもしれません
going to take them to stock your product,
製品の補充にかかる時間を予測し
and use this to predict which supplier you will ask to refill the shelf, and when.
それによって どの供給会社に いつ在庫を再発注するか決めるのです
And of course, all these models themselves might be more complex.
もちろん それぞれのモデルが より複雑である可能性もあります
The model to predict the demand from milk is going to be very
牛乳の需要を予測するモデルと
different from the market to predict the demand for dry noodles.
乾麺の需要を予測するモデルとでは まったく異なり
And the model for restocking electronics is very
電子機器の再発注モデルは
different from the model for restocking furniture.
家具の再発注モデルとはまったく違います
There is not one ML model.
機械学習モデルは1つではありません
There are dozens of ML models per product.
製品ごとに多くの機械学習モデルが存在します
This being a teaching course,
これは教育コースなので
we will show you how to train, deploy,
1つのモデルで訓練、デプロイ
and predict with a single model.
予測を行います
In practice though, you'll be building
しかし実際は多数の機械学習モデルを構築して 問題を解決します
Avoid the trap of thinking of building
単一のモデルで問題を すべて解決しようという考えは
a monolithic one model solves a whole problem solutions.
捨ててください